(Lord Qin's Residence) After receiving your invitation,
接到殿下的帖子
I realized you have such good taste.
甚感殿下雅意
You mentioned
殿下说
you received two good teas
得了两团好茶
and invited me to taste them.
邀我共赏
So, I came here
我就毫不客气
without hesitation.
前来叨扰了
You're so kind, Prime Minister Gu.
顾相客气了
These two plum bonsai trees
这还有两株老梅桩盆景
were sent by Pei Yuan
是裴源到了泌州之后
after he reached Bizhou.
派人给我送过来的
They may not be valuable,
虽不值钱
but they're unique.
但颇有意趣
Martial people like me
我是个粗野之人
don't know about plants.
不懂这些花月之事
But I heard
但我听闻顾相
you're an excellent painter of plum in the capital.
画梅乃是京中一绝
So,
所以
I think having these two bonsai trees with me is a waste.
这两株老梅桩盆景
Later,
回头
I'll deliver them to your mansion.
一并送到顾相府中去
I see.
好
I really appreciate it.
多感殿下盛意
I shall receive your gift.
却之不恭啊
By the way,
对了
the daughter of Cui Yi,
这崔倚的女儿
Miss Cui,
崔氏女
she requested an audience with His Majesty.
要觐见陛下之事
Has the Ministry of Rites sorted this out?
礼部还没争出个分晓吗
Not only it's a controversy in the Ministry of Rites,
不止是礼部争执不下
but now
现在
even the Ministry of War has gotten involved.
连兵部也掺和进来了
They argue
兵部说
that the Cui Army defends against the enemy at the frontier,
崔家军在前方抗敌打仗
Miss Cui should be deemed as the descendant of Great General Cui
崔氏女
to see His Majesty.
去觐见陛下
However, the Ministry of Rites disapproves of it,
可礼部却驳说
saying that there's no precedent for this.
没有此先例
While the Ministry of Revenue claims
而户部又说
that the military provisions and funds of the Cui Army
崔家军的粮草 军饷
weren't allocated by the Ministry of Revenue,
均未从户部拨发
instead, they're deducted from the tax revenues
自从平凉 蔚阳的
of Pingliang and Weiyang.
赋税中扣除
They insist on settling this account.
这笔糊涂账不能不算
As of now,
现在
the six ministries have already started a great dispute
崔氏女还没有见到陛下
even before Miss Cui meets His Majesty.
可是六部自己
Actually,
其实
Ministry of Rites disagrees
这崔氏女要觐见陛下
with Miss Cui seeking an audience
礼部不就是拘泥于
because there isn't any precedent, right?
没有先例吗
Miss Cui's mother, Madam He,
这崔氏女的母亲贺氏
was granted the title Heroic Lady by the court.
是朝廷敕封的武烈夫人
I remember during the Ruijing's reign,
我记得在瑞景年间
to present an honorary plaque to Lady of Wise Assistance,
朝廷为了旌表辅圣夫人
her daughter was summoned
特意在大朝之日
to the court
令辅圣夫人的女儿
to receive a gold plaque
亲自上殿
from Emperor Shizu
由世祖皇帝
during the court meeting.
亲自赐了金表
Your Highness,
殿下真是
thank you for enlightening me.
一语惊醒梦中人哪
I remember this precedent.
确有此先例
In that case,
既然如此
it should be fine
那崔氏女
for Miss Cui to see His Majesty.
便可以上殿觐见陛下了
I just sent someone
我刚刚命人
to look for the record.
去查阅了那份卷宗
As expected,
果然
Lord Qin
溱王前几日
checked this record a few days ago.
也查了这份卷宗
That the daughter of Lady of Wise Assistance entered the court
辅圣夫人的女儿
was an event from 60 years ago.
那是六十多年前的
Only old officials in the Ministry of Rites could find that.
只有礼部的积年老吏
Lord Qin actually searched for the record
溱王为了崔氏女
for the sake of Miss Cui.
特意寻此旧例
This apparently shows his devotion
足见他对崔氏女的
to Miss Cui.
用情之真
For that woman,
为了那崔氏女
he tried every possible means
他千方百计 费尽心思
to fulfill her wish.
想让她得偿所愿哪
Wan.
婉儿
You're smart.
你是个聪明的孩子
If your rival is Miss Cui herself,
倘若你的对手是崔氏女
I believe
为父觉得
you still can give it a try.
你颇可一试
But if your rival
但若你的对手
isn't Miss Cui,
不是崔氏女
but rather Lord Qin's devotion for her,
而是溱王对那崔氏女的
do you think
那你觉得
you stand a chance?
你还有几分胜算呢
If I concede defeat before even trying,
试都不试就自认失败
I don't deserve
那便不配
to be your daughter.
当父亲的女儿了
Besides, nothing is predictable.
何况世事难料
While Lord Qin takes a liking to Miss Cui,
纵然溱王对崔氏女有情
what if Cui Yi is imperious and disrespects the Emperor
但如果崔氏跋扈欺君
and commits treason?
通敌叛国
The entire Cui family would be eliminated,
那别说是择婚皇子了
let alone marrying off his daughter to a prince.
就应该被株连九族
As for Cui Yi,
崔倚这个人呢
he may be imperious and disrespectful towards the Emperor,
说他跋扈欺君或许会有
but he won't
但说他通敌叛国
commit to treason.
那倒不至于
Father.
父亲
Chai Hong, Duke of Fan, the founding General of the Left Martial Guard,
开国左武卫大将军
was accused of treason.
被指通敌叛国
Eventually, he was beheaded in front of the public.
最后被问斩街市
Even the founding general,
就连堂堂开国大将军
Duke of Fan, could be accused of treason,
樊国公都被指通敌叛国
why couldn't that happen to Cui Yi?
那崔倚怎么就不可能呢
Young Lady.
小姐
Someone from the Ministry of Rites came to inform
刚刚礼部派人来说
that you could seek an audience with His Majesty
可以去觐见陛下了
on the court meeting three days later.
就在三日之后
Really?
是吗
It seems
看来他们
that their dispute has led to a protocol at last.
终于争论出了一个章程
They said
反正礼部的人说
it was based
是依照什么
on the previous case of the daughter of Lady of Wise Assistance.
辅圣夫人之女先例
I'm clueless about that.
我也不懂什么意思
Anyway, the conclusion is
总之就是说
that you can meet His Majesty.
小姐可以去觐见陛下了
It's faster than I expected.
这还真比我想得快一些
However, I was told
不过我是听说
that Prime Minister Gu
是顾相
went to the Ministry of Rites in person
亲自去了一趟礼部
to search for a record from 60 years ago.
翻找了大概
Therefore, the Ministry of Rites
所以礼部才这么快
permitted your request in a short time.
同意你去觐见的
A record from 60 years ago?
六十多年前的旧例啊
It must be hard for him to find that.
也难为他能找到
It seems
看来
that Prime Minister Gu is willing to try every possible mean
顾相为了平息朝中争议
to quell the dispute in court.
也真是辛苦用心了
By the way, Young Lady,
对了 小姐
Ear told me
我听耳朵跟我说
that a few days ago, Lord Qin also went
溱王前些日子
to the Ministry of Rites several times.
也去了好几趟礼部
He went there
说是为了什么
to search for case records
边关的事情
of the frontier for several days.
去查了好几天的卷宗
As you know,
你也知道
those case records
那些卷宗啊
have long been left aside.
都多少年没人碰过了
They took quite some days to find it
他们翻找了几天
and got themselves dirty all over.
弄得灰头土脸的
Lord Qin
我看溱王这个人啊
is insincere.
真是挺没意思的
Even Prime Minister Gu
人家顾相都知道
would look for the records to help us.
去为了我们翻找先例
While he
他呢
only cares about himself
只顾自己的事
and ignores you.
对你也不闻不问的
You...
你这
What's wrong with your attire?
你今天怎么穿成这样啊
I'm attending the court meeting.
上朝啊
It's been ages since you went for it.
你都多久没上朝了
From what I know,
我记得你是
you never persisted in going.
三天打鱼两天晒网
Either you skip the meeting
还经常偷懒
or feign sickness.
装病不愿意去
What in the world
今天是哪阵风
woke you up
把你吹起来
to attend the court meeting today?
忽然想上朝了
The weather is fine.
今天天气好
So, I decided to go.
就去上个朝了
The weather is fine?
天气好
Do not forget to bring us
别忘了下朝回来
some fried quails to pair with liquor afterward.
带炸鹌鹑下酒啊
Summon
传
the daughter of Cui Yi, Great General Pingliang,
平凉大将军
Great General Weiyang,
蔚阳大将军
Commander-in-chief of the Shuozhou,
朔州道行军大总管
General of the Left,
左威卫大将军
Cui Lin
崔倚之女崔琳
into the court.
上殿
She's Cui Yi's daughter?
这就是崔倚的女儿
Yes.
是啊
It's out of my expectation.
真没想到啊
I, Cui Lin, greet Your Majesty.
臣女崔琳 参见陛下
Rise.
免
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢陛下
You insisted
既然你说
on seeking my audience
你要代替你的父亲
on your father's behalf.
非要上殿见朕
Go ahead.
有什么事就说吧
I, Cui Lin, present myself to Your Majesty on my father's behalf because of Luoyang.
崔琳代父觐见
The Cui Army briefly seized control of it
于孙靖叛乱之时
during the rebellion led by Sun Jing.
由崔家军暂为代管
Now that the country is in peace
如今 天下平靖
in the early period of your reign,
陛下御极 垂拱之治
the Cui Army
故崔家军
will promptly withdraw from Luoyang
即刻退出泺阳
and return it to the court.
将岽都泺阳归还于朝中
That's good news.
好事啊
You were saying
你是说
you wanted to return Luoyang to me?
要将岽都泺阳还给朕
Yes.
是
Luoyang, belongs to the country.
泺阳是国朝的岽都
Naturally, it belongs to Your Majesty as well.
自然也是陛下的岽都
The Cui Army merely seized command of it temporarily.
崔家军不过是代管而已
Now that the rebellion has subsided,
如今叛乱已平
the Cui Army
崔家军
certainly has to withdraw from Luoyang
当然应该退出泺阳
and return it to the court.
将岽都归还于朝
Good.
好
Very good.
很好
It turns out
原来你上殿
this is your intention to meet me.
是为了说这件事
You should've said it earlier.
早说嘛
Good.
好
I really adore
朕就喜欢
straightforward young people like you.
你这么爽快的孩子
I must tell the Empress
朕要跟皇后说
to set up a banquet
让她好好设宴
to receive you.
好好地款待你
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢陛下
Empress.
皇后啊
When Cui Lin came into the court
今天这个崔琳穿着盔甲
in her armor,
走上大殿的时候
I thought to myself
朕心里就在想
that Cui Yi was a rude man,
这个崔倚如此地无礼
his own daughter
他教出的女儿
must be uncouth as well.
也不会好到哪儿去
Much to my expectation,
可是没想到
Cui Lin straightaway said
崔琳一开口就说
that she wanted to return Luoyang to the court.
要将岽都泺阳还给朝廷
Congratulations.
恭喜陛下
We get to reclaim Luoyang
不费一兵一卒
without using a soldier.
便收回了岽都
Advisor Wu said
吴国师说过了
I'm the emperor
朕是真龙天命
chosen by Heaven.
天命所归
Naturally, I'm blessed with great fortune.
当然是福运绵绵
Just now, Your Majesty mentioned
适才陛下说
about holding a banquet for Miss Cui.
要设宴款待崔小姐
Do you have any expectations for the banquet?
不知 要如何办的才好
As grander as possible.
办得热闹一些
Invite noble ladies.
多叫一些大家闺秀
I want to show Cui Lin
让这个崔琳看看
how noble ladies from the capital behave.
京中真正的大家闺秀
I want to break her spirit.
也好压压她的气焰
Yes.
是
The Cui Army is battling at Shuozhou,
崔家军如今在朔州作战
while the court is wary of them.
朝廷对其猜忌不断
Cui Lin came to the court meeting on her father's behalf
崔琳呢 代父入朝
to return Luoyang.
将岽都泺阳还于朝廷
This move
这步棋大开大合
is bold and straightforward.
果断干脆
Cui Yi
这崔倚行事
is indeed shrewd.
果然是老辣呀
As expected of a seasoned general.
不愧是沙场宿将
From what I know about Miss Cui,
以婉娘对崔氏女的了解
I think
倒觉得
perhaps today's action
或许
was suggested by Cui Lin to her father.
才会有今日此举
Cui Lin
那这个崔琳
is a surprise.
倒是出乎我的意料啊
Father, in your opinion,
在父亲看来
has the court permanently dispelled their suspicion
朝中对于崔倚的猜忌
about Cui Yi,
是完全打消了
or is it just temporary?
还是暂时打消了
Just temporary.
自然是暂时打消
Cui Yi is the general of Pingliang and Weiyang.
崔倚是平凉蔚阳的大将军
He possesses considerable military power.
手握重兵
How could the court not be wary of him?
朝廷怎么可能
Just now, you mentioned
适才父亲提到
that the Empress intends to hold a banquet for Miss Cui
皇后要宴请崔小姐
and invite noble ladies from the capital to accompany her.
会请京中闺秀作陪
I believe
婉娘
I'm qualified to attend the banquet.
是有资格
Certainly.
那是自然
If so, I shall
那就让婉娘
go and have a good look
好好见识见识
at Miss Cui.
这位代父觐见的崔小姐
I thought you'd already
你不是已经
gained some knowledge about her.
颇为了解她了吗
It's different now.
此一时彼一时也
She was in the army back then,
以前她在军中
but she has come to the court.
现在她在庙堂
Father.
父皇
When I saw Miss Cui earlier today,
今日一见这位崔小姐
I was amazed by her appearance.
没想到长的还挺好看的
Besides, she wore the armor,
尤其是身着一身铠甲
which made her look even more unique.
别有一番风姿
I've been thinking
这几天
about one thing these days.
父皇一直在想啊
Although Cui Yi
虽然这个崔倚
has returned Luoyang to me,
把岽都泺阳还给了朕
but I'm worried
但是长此以往
he might bear evil intentions in the future.
难免他会动歪心思
So,
所以啊
it's necessary to keep him close.
还是得好好地笼络他
Cui Yi has only one daughter.
崔倚只有一个女儿
If you marry her,
你若是娶了他女儿
we could reclaim the Cui Army rightfully.
岂不是名正言顺地
Father, this is brilliant.
父皇明鉴
I think this is a good idea.
此事可行
Soon, the Empress
这两天皇后
will hold a banquet for Cui Lin.
要设宴款待崔琳
I asked the Empress
本来我让皇后
to invite a few noble ladies
就叫上几个大家闺秀
to accompany her.
热闹热闹就完事了
However, by the look of it,
可现在看来啊
you, the princesses,
你和公主们
and Li Ni
还有李嶷
should attend the banquet too.
都一起赴宴
The rest are just companions.
他们呢 都是陪客
But for you,
你
you must assess Cui Lin carefully
你要好好看看崔琳
to see
看一看
if she could be your wife.
你到底想不想娶她
No need to force yourself.
别委屈了自己
Thank you, Father.
多谢父皇
I, Cui Lin,
臣女崔琳
greet Your Majesty.
拜见皇后娘娘
Rise.
免礼 免礼
You appeared in the court with armor on a few days ago.
前日 崔小姐着甲上殿
It's said that you exuded
据说 英气勃勃
an impressive aura.
不让须眉
So, I was thinking
我正想着
of meeting
今日
this female general today.
大约能见着一位女将军
Unexpectedly,
没想到今日
you put on the maiden's clothes today.
崔小姐做闺阁女儿装扮
You carry yourself elegantly
却又这般仪态万方
and look gorgeous.
窈窕动人
You flatter me, Your Majesty.
皇后娘娘过誉了
Don't stand on ceremony. Have a seat.
不必拘束 快入座吧
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢娘娘
We have this banquet
今日盛会
to welcome Miss Cui.
一 为崔小姐洗尘
Besides, it's the season of splendid views.
二 为佳景难得
Miss Cui has been living in Yingzhou.
崔小姐久居营州
It's rare for you to come to the capital.
难得来京城
So, today,
今日
I'll have Lord Qi, Lord Qin,
就让齐王 溱王
and other young people
这些个年轻孩子
to accompany you.
招待你游冶尽兴
Let's drink up
今日满饮此杯
as a welcome sign for Miss Cui.
为崔小姐接风
Thank you, Your Majesty.
多谢皇后娘娘
Thank you, Lord Qi.
多谢齐王殿下
Mother, the show of colored-ball snatching is ready.
禀母后
Great.
如此甚好
I was worried
今日设宴
I couldn't prepare anything interesting for you all.
我正愁没个新鲜玩意儿
So, Lord Qi specially arranged
齐王特意从南边
an acrobatic troupe from the south.
寻了新鲜的杂耍班子
Miss Cui
就让崔小姐
and all the guests here,
和今日的诸位客人们
you may feast your eyes on it.
都一起瞧个热闹
How considerate of you, Lord Qi.
齐王殿下费心了
The colored-ball snatching show is the new trend.
这夺彩之戏啊
When the two teams come onstage,
两方上台之后啊
they could only use the silk streamer as their weapon.
只能抢夺彩帛作为武器
They're allowed to trip, stop,
可以使用绊 拦
wrestle, block, or tangle
摔 挡 绕等方式
to halt the rival's action.
来阻拦对方
The team that first snatches the colored ball
以首先夺得彩球的一方
will be the winner.
作为胜方
Lord Qi is so caring
齐王殿下对崔家小姐
for Miss Cui.
真可谓用心十足
Of course.
能不用心吗
After all, her father commands military power.
毕竟她的父亲手握重兵
If he manages to get the Cui family on his side,
既拉拢了崔家
he's very likely to secure the position as the crown prince.
何愁不能储位东宫
No wonder a general's daughter
也无怪乎她一个臣女
dares to request
竟然上书
to choose a prince as her husband.
要自择皇子为婿
How daring.
好生霸道啊
Both teams
这两队之人
have to figure out
一边要想着
how to kick their rival off the stage
如何将对方踢于台下
while thinking about how to snatch the colored ball.
一边呢
At the same time,
同时呢
they have to watch themselves
还要提防自己
from being kicked off the stage.
不被踢下台
The show
这夺彩之戏呀
is exciting.
甚是激烈
It sounds very interesting.
听着十分有意思呢
It's not fun enough
咱们就这么看着
if we just watch it.
不够热闹
Why don't we make a bet
要不 按照京中旧俗
according to the custom in the capital?
来博个彩头吧
You can place any bets you want. It's just for fun.
不拘多少 好玩罢了
Mother, that's a good idea.
母后所言 如此甚好
Miss Cui, you're the guest.
崔小姐远来是客
Please place your bet.
就请崔小姐博个头彩吧
Yes.
是
Miss Cui, place the bet
崔小姐看好哪一队
on the team you think they might win.
便可以押哪一队
Place the bet
将彩头置于金盘之上
on the gold tray.
就是押彩了
Later, Miss Cui
一会儿由崔小姐
will toss the silk streamer onto the stage
将彩帛掷于台上
to start the show.
便算是开彩
Lord Qi, which team will you choose?
齐王殿下看好哪一队呢
I think
我看
the red team is agile.
红队的人机敏灵巧
They are sure to win.
定是能旗开得胜
If so, I place the bet
那我就押
on the team you choose.
殿下看好的这一队
I bet on the red team.
我押红队胜
My bet is a golden bracelet.
以这只金镯为彩头
Lord Qin, do you want to place your bet?
溱王殿下可要下注
Your Highness.
殿下
Please allow me
让婉娘
to choose for you.
大胆为殿下选一队吧
Which team would you like to choose?
你想选哪一队
I believe
婉娘自然觉得
the blue team will win.
蓝队可胜
All right.
行
I'll bet on the blue team
那我就替顾小姐
on Miss Gu's behalf.
选蓝队胜
This jade pendant is my bet.
这玉鱼作为彩头
You're generous, Ni.
三弟豪阔呀
So generous.
豪阔
Miss Cui, please enjoy the show.
崔小姐 敬请观赏吧
Bravo.
好
Fortunately, I didn't fail you by my choice.
幸不辱命
Your Highness, you have sharp eyes.
殿下好眼光
Giving the rest
其余的
to the red team.
都赏给获胜的红队吧
Miss Cui, which team
崔小姐觉得
should we bet on in the next round?
下一局该押哪一队呢
I think we should stick with the red team.
我觉得还是要押红队
The red team will surely thrive
我看红队呀 风头正盛
on their success.
一定能连胜
Pass my order.
传令下去
All guests enjoyed the show today.
今日大家尽兴
Regardless of which team wins,
无论哪队获胜
reward them handsomely.
全部都赏百金
Wait.
且慢
This time, I'll participate in the show.
这次 我要亲自上场
Lai.
二哥
You enjoy having fun.
平日里
Do you care
可愿意与我
to compete with me?
上场一试
Um...
这
Lord Qi.
齐王殿下
I'd like to
崔琳愿意上场
be your partner
跟殿下搭档
for snatching the ball.
为之一搏
With your help,
有崔小姐相助
we'll surely win the game.
定能拿下此局
Ni.
可是 三弟
We have two people here,
我们是两人
you're only alone.
你却是一人
It's not fair for you.
对你不公平啊
Why don't you
不如
pick one from the troupe
你从这杂耍班子里
to be your partner?
再挑一人作为搭档如何
No need.
不必了
I can handle this.
我以一敌二即可
Lord Qin.
溱王殿下
If you don't despise
殿下若不嫌弃
my clumsiness,
婉娘身手笨拙
I'd like to be your partner.
婉娘愿与殿下搭档上场
Miss Gu.
顾小姐
The game is dangerous.
这夺彩之戏颇为危险
Don't worry.
殿下不必多虑
I know.
婉娘明白的
All right.
好
If so, you'll go with me.
那你便同我一起
Knowing you enjoy this so much,
既如此有兴
go to the treasury
从内帑
to bring a pair of dragon and phoenix hairpins.
取一对龙凤钗来
I'd like to sweeten the pot.
为你们添作彩头
They'll be the prize for you.
待我亲自为你们开彩
Thank you, Mother.
谢母后
We can run a pastry store.
你说
What do you say?
这样的点心铺子怎么样
I was just saying.
我就提了那么一嘴
You're taking it seriously?
你还真打算上了
Of course.
当然了
I take every word you say seriously.
你说的每一句话
Actually,
其实呢
running a pastry store
开一家这样的点心铺子
can be a good idea.
不失为一个好想法
Besides,
而且啊
I've noticed
我看街上那些
stores that sell trinkets
卖小玩意儿的店铺
are quite popular as well.
生意也很是红火呢
Many misses and madams
还有那些胭脂水粉铺子
like to visit rouge stores too.
很多小姐夫人都很喜欢
Good.
好
We'll open a store to sell the things you like.
你喜欢什么
Silly.
傻样
The Empress holds a banquet today.
今天皇后设宴
How will
你说
it turn out?
这宴会到底怎么样了呀
I wonder if Lord Qin and Young Lady
也不知道溱王和小姐
will meet each other.
他们俩见上了没有
They will.
一定会见到的
Mister Shiqi likes Miss Cui very much.
十七郎那么喜欢崔小姐
He'll try his best
他一定会好好地
to coax Miss Cui.
哄崔小姐的
Hopefully, they can make peace with each other soon.
希望他俩赶紧和好吧
Otherwise,
要不然
I'll feel bad for them
咱俩成日这么好的
if they see us getting so close
他们要是再不和好
when they're in disputes.
我可太内疚了
I feel sorry for Young Lady.
真觉得对不起小姐
They will reconcile.
一定会的
How could you do that?
你怎么可以这样
It seems you may have forgotten
溱王殿下忘记了
this is who I am.
崔某
Bravo.
好
Excellent.
好 好 好
Miss Cui.
崔小姐
You're a heroine.
巾帼英雄
Today, Miss Cui
今日崔小姐
really blows my mind.
真让我等大开眼界
Miss Cui,
崔小姐
you're indeed a warrior who fought on the battlefield.
不愧是上过战场的人
The show
如此夺彩之戏
was epic.
也精妙纷呈
This is your reward, Miss Cui.
这是崔小姐的彩头
Thank you, Your Majesty.
多谢皇后娘娘
This pair of dragon and phoenix hairpins
这对龙凤钗
is an art by great hands.
不愧是内省重工
They are exquisite.
细巧非常
Your Majesty.
皇后娘娘
May I have your permission
您赠我的这对龙凤钗
to give the hairpins to someone else?
我可以转赠给他人吗
This is your reward.
既然是你的彩头
You can handle it the way you want.
自然任你处置
Thank you.
谢娘娘
Thank you for being generous, Your Highness.
多承溱王殿下相让
I'd like to present this hairpin
娘娘赏的这支钗子
to you
便聊表心意
as my token of gratitude.
转赠溱王
Lord Qi and Lord Qin
齐王殿下 溱王殿下
are men,
皆是男子
and I'm fighting on the battlefield.
而我也是
However, Miss Gu has always been sheltered in the boudoir.
唯有顾小姐素处闺阁
But she bravely took the initiative to join the game
今日却自告奋勇上台
and didn't squeak
虽然不慎受伤
when she got injured.
却没有一声叫痛
Therefore, I'd like to present this hairpin
那这支凤钗
to Miss Gu
便转赠给顾小姐
as an appreciation for your bravery today.
以慰你今日之勇
Thank you, Miss Cui.
多谢崔小姐
I'm just giving you a gift
都是娘娘的赏赐
that's prepared by Her Majesty.
我不过是借花献佛罢了
Lord Qin,
溱王殿下
both you and Miss Gu
当与顾小姐一起
shall thank Her Majesty for her grace.
谢过皇后娘娘恩典
Rightfully so.
理应如此
Thank you, Mother.
谢母后
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢皇后娘娘
You may rise.
不须多礼
Please take a seat.
你们都入座吧
Yes.
是
Kind lady, come on here.
好孩子 你快过来
Your Majesty.
娘娘
You have a delicate and pretty look,
生得这么娇妍秀美
but you also exude the heroic spirit.
偏又英气过人
The rarest thing is,
最难得的是
you're generous and thoughtful.
你这般大方周全
After knowing Gu Wan'niang's injury,
适才我得知顾婉娘受伤
I intended
本想待会儿
to give her a pair of pear earrings
赠她一对珍珠耳环
to comfort her.
抚慰一二
But you've already thought of that.
你却已经替我想到了
Please don't blame me.
娘娘不怪我唐突才好
I won't.
怎么会呢
Just now,
刚才在台上
you looked like
我看着你
a light and agile sparrow onstage.
就如同一只燕子一般
Lord Qin
溱王
is regarded as a brave fighter.
素日有勇猛无敌的名头
Yet, you won.
今日你却赢了他
Apparently,
可见呀
you're a cut
你确实比他
above him.
还更胜一筹呢
You're flattering me, Your Majesty.
皇后娘娘过誉了
You must be hungry, right?
饿了吧
Start the banquet.
开宴吧
Yes.
是
Please return to your seat.
你快回去休息
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢娘娘
Miss Gu.
顾小姐
Let me give you a toast.
来 我敬你一杯
Lord Qi.
齐王殿下
The water spreads far and wide.
碧波万顷
What a crisp autumn day today.
秋高云淡
Rafting on Taiye Pond
如果在花好月圆之夜
above the shimmering water
泛舟这太液池上
in the mid-autumn night
波光映月
will be a marvelous view to imagine.
想来 风光甚美
Indeed, it's marvelous.
春花秋月各有佳时
However, in the eyes of yours,
只是在崔小姐眼中
beautiful sceneries
四时美景
can never be more interesting
皆不如一展胸中宏图
than your ambition.
来得有趣吧
You resent me.
你心中恼恨我
Everyone has their own pursuit. I can't resent you.
人各有志 我何必恨你
But you look upset.
我看你是生气的样子
I lost the game,
既然输了
so I'm not happy.
自然是有些不悦
I'm afraid
恐怕
you're not happy because you lost money,
你不是生气输了钱
it's because I kissed you.
而是生气我为什么亲你
Yes.
是啊
How could you do an inappropriate act like that?
你怎能行如此轻薄之举
It'd be troublesome
今日人多
if people saw it.
若是被旁人看到还了得
If so, will you tell others?
那你会不会告诉别人
It's not the behavior of a gentleman.
非君子所为
Naturally, I won't.
我自然不会告诉别人
Thank you.
谢谢你
I know
我知道是你
you went to the Ministry of Rites to look for
去礼部查阅了卷宗
the previous records
找出从前成例
and helped me to meet His Majesty
我才可以顺利入朝
in the court.
去觐见陛下
No need to thank me.
你不必谢我
It's my duty to placate Great General Cui
安抚大将军 为君分忧
and share His Majesty's burden.
本就是我该做的
Your Highness,
溱王殿下
looking at your decent actions,
一本正经的样子
I really feel ashamed of myself.
崔某还真是
It's Li Lai. Let's leave.
李崃 走
This is strange.
怪了
The eunuch told me
这内侍明明说
she came to the Taiye Pond.
是往太液池这边来的
How come I see no sign of her?
怎么没瞧见人影
Miss Cui.
崔小姐
Lord Qi.
齐王殿下
I'm leaving the palace
赐宴结束之后
after the banquet.
我也要出宫去
I can see you off.
正好送送崔小姐
Thank you so much.
那就有劳殿下了
You did excellent
适才夺彩之时
during the game just now.
崔小姐赢得实在是精彩
I'm very impressed by you.
令本王大开眼界
You flatter me.
殿下过誉了
Those were just
那些不过都是
some cheap skills.
玩乐的雕虫小技
If it wasn't for you,
若不是有崔小姐在的话
we wouldn't have won Lord Qin
又怎能赢得了溱王
and claimed the reward.
夺得彩头呢
Because you have discerning eyes
那是殿下眼光好
to bet it right.
所以才押得中
Isn't that Miss Cui?
那不是崔小姐吗
Your Highness.
殿下
Miss Gu.
顾小姐
Is your injury all right?
你的伤没事吧
I have a remedy that prevents scars
我府中有伤药
in my residence.
用了之后不留疤
I'll have my men send it to you.
回头让人给你送一些
Thank you, Your Highness.
多谢殿下
You're welcome.
客气了
May I ask
不知崔小姐
what's your hobby?
平日都有些什么爱好
Nanny likes
你送来的玫瑰荔枝樱花酪
the rose lychee plum pasty you gave.
奶娘吃了说特别好吃
She wants me to thank you again.
让我再三多谢你
Since Nanny likes it,
既然奶娘喜欢
I shall invite her to the store to taste it.
下回我请她去店铺里
It's said that riding horse on Wonderland during autumn
素闻秋日里
- is a great experience. - Thank you.
多谢
I believe tomorrow
我看明日
will be a good day.
必定是个好天气
Why don't we
不如明日我陪崔小姐
visit Wonderland tomorrow?
去趟乐游原吧
That's very kind of you.
殿下客气了
But
只是
I need to go to Ci'en Temple to thank the deity for answering my prayer.
明日我要去慈恩寺还愿
I can go there with you.
那我陪你去慈恩寺
Your Highness.
殿下
Lord Qi.
齐王殿下
His Majesty requests for you.
陛下传您
It's a deal, then.
就这么说定了
I'll go to Ci'en Temple with you tomorrow.
明日我陪你去慈恩寺
I need to meet my father now.
我先去见父皇了
Don't forget.
说定了
Tomorrow morning, I'll have my men pick you up at your residence.
明日一早
Miss Cui
这位崔小姐
is truly remarkable.
真是太厉害了
She actually returned Luoyang to the court.
居然把泺阳还给了朝廷
Indeed.
确实
Luoyang and Xichang are near to each other.
岽都与西长京近在咫尺
Given the current situation,
如今这个局面
if the Cui family continues to occupy Luoyang,
他崔家若是再占着泺阳
I'm afraid
恐怕
it'll only do more harm to them.
只有百害而无一益呀
Isn't this
这难道不是那位
Great General Cui's idea?
崔大将军的主意
Probably,
我认为
it's Cui Lin's.
恐怕是崔琳的主张
She went to the court meeting
她入朝上殿
to return Luoyang.
归还岽都
Hence,
那么
her marriage with a prince
择皇子为婿之事
is going
她恐怕
to be a done deal.
八成能够称心如意呀
Does Miss Cui
那这位崔小姐
want to be Crown Princess?
是想做太子妃
Crown Princess?
太子妃
Everyone knows Crown Prince sits in a difficult position,
人人都会觉得太子难为
but no one has ever been concerned
可是谁又关心过
about Crown Princess.
太子妃的处境呢
Even the most intelligent person
再聪慧的人
has to restrain
到了东宫中
their glow
也得敛起羽翼
when they finally take over the Eastern Palace.
收起锋芒
Miss Cui
这位崔姑娘
is born straightforward by nature.
本性率真
Besides,
她又是一个
she has a carefree soul.
这么洒脱的人
If she really becomes the Crown Princess,
若真的做了太子妃
it's a woe to her.
那就太可惜了
Your Highness.
娘娘
Jin'niang.
锦娘
I brought you
我是
to the palace from my maiden family.
从娘家把你带进宫的
I used to be a capricious person.
从前我是一个
However, since I married into the Eastern Palace,
自从嫁到东宫
my character has changed.
我就变成了
As Crown Princess,
作为太子妃
I have to be virtuous and generous.
要贤良 大度
In such desperate states
身逢大变
where Crown Prince has died
太子身死
and the great imperial grandson is in exile,
太孙流落
I had to deal with Sun Jing
我不惜与孙靖周旋
to fight for a chance
也想尽力争取
to restore the Dayu.
我大裕光复的机会
I understand
娘娘心里苦
you're suffering inside.
奴婢都知道
I'll tell Crown Prince everything
将来我到了地下
when I'm six feet under.
我就会亲口对太子说
I did my best.
我尽力了
I fulfilled my responsibility
我尽了一个做太子妃
as Crown Princess.
应尽的责任
Even if I would be thrown into infamy,
甚至是背上千古骂名
I wouldn't care.
我都不会顾忌
The thing is, Jin'niang,
可是锦娘
I can no longer recognize myself.
我都不认得我自己了
When history mentions me,
史书上写到我
it'll only be a few short lines
也就是寥寥的一句话
saying that I'm a disloyal woman.
也许会骂我不贞
But I've done so much.
可是我做了那么多
I'm confused
我到底是谁
who I am now.
我都不知道了
Your Highness.
娘娘
You can cry.
您哭一场吧
Have a good cry.
好好地哭一场
No, I can't.
不
Ever since I've become the Crown Princess,
自从我做了太子妃
I told myself
我就告诉我自己
not to be weak and not to cry.
不能再软弱和流泪了
I mustn't forget
我不能忘
that I was once the Crown Princess of the Dayu.
我曾是大裕王朝的
Last night, in the middle of the night,
昨天晚上大半夜呀
I heard Mister Shiqi
我又听见十七郎
was practicing with his sword again.
在院子里练剑呢
I suppose he didn't sleep all night.
估计是一宿没睡
It's normal that he can't sleep
相思病嘛
when he suffers from lovesickness.
睡不着那是应该的
Isn't Miss Cui at Xichang?
不是 那崔小姐
Yes, but so what?
在就不能害相思病吗
Then why must he suffer?
在都在了相思什么呀
You don't know.
你不懂
You do?
你懂
Have you ever touched a woman's hand?
你摸过女人的手吗你
Do you know better than I do? Have you touched a woman's hand?
那你懂
- I did. - Did you?
我摸过 你摸过吗
- I know. - I did.
我懂 我懂 我懂
Fine. Enough.
行了 行了 行了
Eat the congee.
喝粥吧
Mister Shiqi.
十七郎
Where are you going early in the morning?
你这么早去哪儿啊
I'm going for a walk.
去散散心
You said
你昨天不是说
you wanted to give Miss Gu the ointment yesterday.
要给顾小姐送药膏吗
Who's sending it over?
叫谁去啊
Are you sending it yourself?
难不成亲自去呀
You go.
你去吧
Fine. I shouldn't have asked.
得 我就不该问
Mister Shiqi.
十七郎
Don't you have anything to give Miss Cui?
你就没有什么东西
No.
没有
Why does he send medicine to Miss Gu
为什么他给顾小姐
and not to Miss Cui?
却不送东西给崔小姐呢
How am I supposed to know?
你问我 我问谁啊
- You don't know.
你不懂
Come here and eat this.
来 过来吃点 快快快
Greetings, Your Highness.
见过齐王殿下
Where's Miss Cui?
你家小姐呢
We promised
我跟她约好了
to visit Ci'en Temple.
同游慈恩寺的
Miss Cui
我们家小姐
went out this morning.
一大早就出门去了
Last night, she lit incense and divined for an auspicious hour to go out.
她昨晚特意拈香
The sign showed it should be quarter to seven in the morning.
说得卯正三刻出门才好
Besides,
还特意说
she can't bring anyone with her
不许带任何人去
to show sincerity.
这样才显得心诚
I wasn't allowed to tag along.
连我都不许跟去呢
However, Young Lady instructed me
不过小姐特意嘱咐我
to wait here
让我在府中
and relayed a message to you.
等着齐王殿下
She's very sorry
跟殿下说声十分抱歉
to make you come here for nothing.
让您白跑一趟了
Never mind.
无妨
I'll meet her at Ci'en Temple.
我去慈恩寺找她去
I bid you farewell, Your Highness.
殿下慢走
It seems simple.
看着挺简单的
But I can't weave it properly.
怎么就是编不好
What brings you here?
你怎么来这儿了
I was thinking
本想着
of taking a stroll,
出来走走
but ended up here.
结果走到这儿
I was just following my will.
大概是不由自主吧
I didn't expect
没想到
to see you here.
在这里遇到你
I didn't want to go to Ci'en Temple.
我并不想去什么慈恩寺
I know.
我知道
Since we met here,
既然遇上了
Shiqi,
十七郎
can you accompany me today?
你能不能答应我
Just today,
就这一天
you're not Lord Qin,
你不是溱王
and I'm not Miss Cui.
我也不是什么崔小姐
Let's stay together
无忧无虑地
carefreely and happily for one day.
快乐地过上一天
All right?
好吗
All right.
好 我答应你
Do you remember
还记不记得
you promised me
当初你答应过我
that if one day
如果有一天
the world nestles in peace,
天下平定
we would
就陪我一起
ride on horses across the plains of Wonderland?
驰马乐游原
Ying.
阿萤
Once the country nestles in peace,
待到天下太平
let's go
你我并肩
and have fun in Wonderland?
同游乐游原
Deal.
一言为定
For whatever we said
说过的话
and promises we made,
许过的愿
perhaps none will come true,
或许都兑现不了
but I really hope
但是我很希望
that this day will come,
能有这么一天
even if it's only 24 hours.
哪怕只有十二个时辰
We leave everything behind
我们俩什么都不想
and spend a happy
快快乐乐
and carefree day together.
无忧无虑地过一天
All right?
好吗
All right, I promise you.
好 我答应你
Back then, you often said
以前你常常说
that you wished
要是能早点认识我
you could meet me earlier.
就好了
I still feel the same now.
现在我也这么觉得
If I could meet you earlier,
如果我能早点认识你
I would've taken you to Yingzhou
我就会带你去营州
to admire the apricot blossom
去看杏花
and taste apricots.
去吃小白杏
Let's not talk about this.
不要说这些了
Today, we're going
我们先开开心心
to be happy today.
过好今天
All right?
好不好
Crystal clear water pond in autumn
秋波澄净 秋水长天
This is picturesque.
这里可真美啊
It reminds me
这让我想起了
of the days in Laolan Pass.
在牢兰关的时候
Every autumn,
每到秋天
Bao would go to hunt Mongolian gazelle by the riverside.
老鲍就会在河边打黄羊
We ate roasted mutton every day.
然后每天都烤羊肉吃
You're making me hungry.
说得我都饿了
I can go down to catch fish.
我下水给你抓鱼吃
Sure.
好呀
Shiqi.
十七郎
Over there.
那儿 那儿 那儿
There's a big fish.
那儿有条大鱼
Yes, over there.
对 那边
Catch this.
接着
To think
没想到我们阿萤
a good writer
文能下笔千言
and a brave warrior like Ying
武能上阵杀敌
can't even deal with a fish.
居然连条鱼都对付不了
To think Shiqi
没想到我们十七郎
finally caught a fish
忙活了半天
after great efforts
好不容易抓条鱼
but didn't deliver the fish properly to my hands.
也没有好好地
Let's try again.
再来
Behind you.
你后面
Behind.
后面 后面 后面
In front.
前面
Hurry.
快点
Do you like it?
怎么样 好吃吗
Shiqi roasted the fish
十七郎连烤的鱼
so well.
都这么好吃
You're indeed a peerless talent.
真是不世之才
Your compliment
你这么一夸我
sounds unnerving to me, though.
我就心惊胆战
I think I smell a rat.
我总觉得哪里
I'm not complimenting you.
我这不是在夸你
I'm complimenting myself.
我是在自夸呢
Complimenting yourself?
自夸
You see,
你看
the Shiqi I like
我喜欢的十七郎
is so astonishingly talented.
是如此惊才绝艳
Doesn't that mean my taste
那我是不是眼光绝佳
is excellent?
是不是很厉害呢
To me,
你在我心里
you're always the best
一直最好
and most exceptional.
也最厉害
You're complimenting me,
这明明是在夸我
but it sounds like
但是听起来
you're complimenting yourself.
好像你也是在自夸呢
Certainly.
那是自然
The Ying I adore
我喜欢的阿萤
is so astonishingly talented.
就是这样惊才绝艳
Likewise, my taste
我明明也眼光绝佳
is excellent.
十分厉害呀